Guide to the Robert M. Rosenzweig Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Robert M. Rosenzweig papers
1962-1983
SC0632
Rosenzweig, Robert M.
4.5 Linear feet
Correspondence files reflecting Rosenzweig's work as Dean of the Graduate Division, Vice-Provost, and Vice-President for Public Affairs, with some articles and speeches.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Robert M. Rosenzweig, 2002
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Biography
Robert M. Rosenzweig was born in Detroit on August 27, 1931. He received his bachelor's degree in political science from the University of Michigan in 1952 and his master's degree the following year. In 1956, he received his Ph.D. in political science from Yale.
Rosenzweig joined the Stanford University staff in 1962 after serving as an instructor at Yale and Amherst, a Congressional Fellow of the American Political Science Association, and special assistant to the United States Commissioner of Education. Rosenzweig started at Stanford as associate dean of the Graduate Division and a lecturer in political science. In 1967, he was promoted to associate provost by President Wallace Sterling. During this time (1967-68), Rosenzweig also served as the director for the Center for Research in International Studies.
In May 1971, he was named vice-provost and advisor to President Richard W. Lyman. He held this position until December 1974, when he became the first vice-president for public affairs. His duties in this position included responsibility for Stanford's federal, state and community government relations, news and public services, public event programs, and other public affairs activities.
During his time at Stanford, Rosenzweig was a consultant on international programs to the Ford Foundation and he represented Stanford within the Association of Independent California Colleges and Universities (AICCU). In 1978, he was elected vice-president of the AICCU and in 1980 he was elected president. He was also a member of the Committee on International Studies and the Committee of Fifteen, a joint student-faculty administration group, and he was a director of the Far West Laboratory for Educational Research and Development.
In 1983, Rosenzweig left Stanford to head the Association of American Universities in Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content
This collection consists primarily of Rosenzweig's correspondence files, including chronological files of outgoing letters reflecting all of his Stanford positions, 1963-83, general correspondence files (both incoming and outgoing), 1962-1979, and copies of Paul Hanna's correspondence, 1967-68, pertaining to the Seminar on the role of Higher Education in National Development in Asia, held in Seoul, Korea in August 1968. Other papers include drafts, published text, and correspondence pertaining to articles and reviews by Rosenzweig, 1962-78; text of his speeches and statements, 1971-78; and drafts of statements he prepared for other University administrators.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Graduate Division.; Stanford University. Office of the Provost.; College administrators.; Universities and colleges--Administration.; Universities and colleges--Public relations
Collection Contents
- Chron files, January 1963-May 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1-44)
- Chron files, June 1977-May 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1-32)
- Chron file, Paul Hanna, Stanford International Development Education Center [SIDEC], Sep-Dec 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Chron file, Paul Hanna, SIDEC, Nov 1967-Jan1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Chron file, Paul Hanna, SIDEC, Jan-Feb 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Chron file, Paul Hanna, SIDEC, Mar-68 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Chron file, Paul Hanna, SIDEC, Apr-Jun 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Chron file, Paul Hanna, SIDEC, July 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Chron file, Paul Hanna, SIDEC, Aug-Sep 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- General correspondence, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- General correspondence, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- General correspondence, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- General correspondence, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- General correspondence, 1966-67 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Personal correspondence, 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Personal correspondence (holiday cards), 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Personal correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Personal correspondence, Feb-Apr 1971 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Personal correspondence, May - June 1971 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Personal correspondence, Jul-Dec 1971 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Personal correspondence, Jan-Jun 1972 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Personal correspondence, Aug-Sep 1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Personal correspondence, Oct-72 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Personal correspondence, Nov-Dec 1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Personal correspondence, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Personal correspondence, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Personal correspondence, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Personal correspondence, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Personal correspondence, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Personal correspondence, 1978-79 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Trip to Milan, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Trip to China (Stanford Alumni Assoc.), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Reprints and publications (correspondence), 1963-79 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- RMR, reviews (correspondence), 1963-68 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- RMR, letter to Stanford Daily, 26-Oct-70 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- RMR, Title IV article (correspondence), 1962-63 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- RMR, The Reach of the Submerged, Stanford Today, text and correspondence, 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- RMR, Who Wants to Govern the University? Educational Record, text and correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- RMR, Public Policy for Graduate Education, drafts, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- RMR, After Bakke, AGB Reports, photocopy, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- RMR, drafts of items for Pres. Lyman and others, 1973-74 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- RMR, statements, debates and articles, 1971-72 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- RMR, speeches and statements, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- RMR, speeches and statements, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- RMR, speeches and statements, 1977-78 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- RMR, debate with Yale Braunstein re campus judicial procedure, 1-Mar-72 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- RMR, speech honoring David Saxon, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Owen Spann talk show, background materials for, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Franklin case: Advisory Board Report, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- William F. Miller, statements and correspondence, 1972-74 (Box 3, Folder 48)